the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to perform Hello friends
I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a professor of
Kinesiology in the center for sport
performance at Cal State Fullerton in
today's show we're going to jump
straight into the application of
training for muscle hypertrophy and
strength and power in order to do that
what I'd like to spend our time on is to
go through a couple of actual programs
that are designed to maximize both of
those goals these are programs I have
used myself as well as in my laboratory
and they come from some of the world's
most foremost experts in training for
strength and power as well as muscle
hypertrophy so as I stated a second ago
Today's Show is directly about the
application and we'll talk very briefly
here in a second about what these terms
mean some overarching principles that
are going to be true across both of
those programs and a little bit of
context but I don't want to spend a lot
of time going over the overarching
philosophy
or background physiology because I've
done that in other shows as well as many
other places and you can get that uh
through any of the links in our show
notes so today really is about the
programs so we want to get into that
walk you through why they're being built
uh what the terms mean how they're
structured the way they are and then of
course give you these samples for free
and so that is to say both of the
programs I'm going to discuss today are
available completely free and in their
entirety in our show notes now before we
do that we have to explain some terms
when I say strength what I mean more
specifically is force production think
about this as muscular strength or my
one repetition maximum it doesn't
actually have to be a one repetition
maximum could be a two or three or five
that's not the point it's really
differentiating it from muscle size and
muscle power so muscle strength
represents your ability to apply Force
to stop movement from happening when you
don't want it to move to control your
joints to control objects and to control
other people if that's the application
so it really is about that muscle size
is different we call that muscle
hypertrophy there's obviously a strong
relationship between muscle size and
muscle strength but it's not perfect
either there's clearly an overlap but
just because you maximize strength
doesn't mean you maximize size and the
inverse inverse is true as well
maximizing size does not maximize
strength the easiest most uh practical
example I can give you here is take two
of the sports that spend they're most
time focusing on these goals in the one
hand let's just call it bodybuilding
where the goal is to maximize physical
size and we'll contrast that to the
sport of powerlifting now this may sound
a little bit confusing but trust me in
the terminology here powerlifting is a
sport in which they test maximal
strength okay now in the sake of a
bodybuilder whether you're male or
female it doesn't matter if you're
increasing muscle size and your goal is
to optimize for that specific outcome
almost surely you're going to get
stronger all early in the training
medium in the training probably several
years into your training you're going to
be getting a lot stronger there's no
question but you're not going to be
maximizing your strength if we were to
look at the powerlifter you'd see a
similar thing often times they put on
muscle along their training Journey but
they're maximizing and trying to Peak
for physical strength and so maybe six
months in a training the amount of
muscle size and muscle strength gains
would be equal between a powerlifter and
a bodybuilder but maybe after 6 months
months well certainly after 6 years
eventually you'll start seeing
separation where the powerlifter will
get stronger at a faster rate than the
bodybuilder will but the bodybuilder
will add muscle at a faster rate than
the power lifter would be so I hope that
makes sense they are complimentary but
they are really quite different so if
you're at the very very very very
beginning of your strength training
history and this is your first jump into
it you may not notice or feel or
understand really the functional
difference between training for strength
versus hypertrophy but the months and
years go on you will start to know that
and so that means it's important to
apply the right type of programming to
make sure you get the right outcome
you're looking for so if you're trying
to add muscle but you're using Concepts
that are better applied for strength and
power you're probably going to be
leaving some gains on the table which
means you'll be unhappy with your
results right you won't be getting the
progress you're looking for the same
thing could be said If you're trying to
gain strength but you're using
hypertrophy or muscle size principles
again you might be going man I'm not
getting stronger I'm not getting faster
more powerful I'm doing the things that
I saw they're supposed to be correct
they're scientifically validated etc etc
but you're applying the wrong principle
because it came from a different body of
literature so that alone can hopefully
save you quite a bit of headache and can
get you to your results much faster so
with all that in mind the last variable
to talk about here is muscle power and
that differs from strength in that it is
force multiplied by velocity so again as
I said a second ago strength is
effectively Force production power is
force multiplied by velocity another way
you could come up with this equation is
work over time so how much work can you
complete over a certain amount of time
power tends to be most important for
sport application though not always but
typically is the one you're more
concerned with almost all sports if you
had to choose between being more
powerful or more strong or stronger
rather you would choose power and the
reason is sports typically work on a
Time domain so think about this way
let's say I'm going up against you and
we're going to collide together rugby
doesn't matter right and you can produce
a th NS in the ground and I can produce
500 but it takes you two seconds to
produce your
1,000 and it takes me 300 milliseconds
so a third of 1 second to produce my 500
well by the time we actually Collide
most sports occur in the 200 to 400
millisecond range I will have maybe 400
newtons produced you've only produced
300 Newtons CU you're not even halfway
to your peak time and now I'll own that
exchange because I'm actually much
functionally stronger than you lots of
different examples we can think about
there but that's really what we're
talking about when we're differentiating
strength and power the majority of the
application I'm going to give you here
this program was actually developed for
someone looking to maximize both
strengths and power so we're not going
to split that up into individual
programs right now because there is
clearly uh an overlap there in fact if
you were to dive into this a little bit
more deeply
you'll realize that actually power is
simply Force time velocity so if I know
how much force you can produce now I
need to know your velocity I can
generate what's called a force velocity
curve such that where on that curve of
if it's too heavy and I slow down that's
not a lot of power but if it's really
really really fast but that means I have
to go to a lightweight it's not a lot of
power either so some point on that curve
we get this peak power Direction where
it's not too heavy but it's not too slow
or it's not too fast and light either
that's really power and so by enhancing
velocity I typically have the
opportunity to enhance Power by
enhancing Force I also have the
opportunity to enhance power and so
almost all power programs will have a
force component as well as a velocity
component and the program I'm going to
go through here in a few short minutes
we'll cover both aspects of that and so
again to reiterate that program is
designed and built for both strength and
power because it was built for a
field-based sport athlete now while I
did just say this program is for
athletes I do want to make sure we are
crystal clear here this is not only for
athletes you've maybe heard me say this
many many times but if you have a body
you're an athlete we all have a need to
have sufficient muscle mass we all have
a need to be powerful and to be strong
whether you want to use those skills and
abilities and talents to be better at a
sport for or to be better at life I
don't care but we're going to have a
hard time being successful in life if we
have insufficient muscle strength and
power we're going to cover these things
in detail in other episodes and have and
I've done it in numerous other places
but just really quickly your skeletal
muscle is one of the most important
organs in your entire body it's the
largest organ which means it's
responsible for a whole host of things
first and foremost Locomotion it is the
thing that gets you throughout this
world if you don't have muscle or your
muscle is not strong or powerful and
remember while just because you have
muscle doesn't mean you're strong or
powerful and just because you're strong
and powerful doesn't mean you have a lot
of muscle but there is still a massive
overlap it is hard to be really really
really strong and powerful with very
little muscle take a look at any weight
class-based sport that's why they're
there typically as you add muscle you
also add Peak and maximal strength and
so there's a relationship there really
challenging for most people unless you
are highly trained and skilled in
understanding exercise physiology and
exercise science to have enough strength
and power and really to be under muscled
and so for most people listening who are
not athletes or working with highle
strength add conditioning professionals
you're going to want to make sure you've
got some muscle and some power because
again that's the thing that lets you
move through this world you can imagine
simple scenarios like running through
the terminal in an airport with your
luggage trying to catch your layover
probably the most common example we'll
give are things like stopping yourself
and bracing yourself from a fall as you
age in life becomes incredibly important
but really functionality so let's just
say that you want to walk up some stairs
or go on a hike and every step
represents such a high percentage of
your maximum leg strength it becomes
extremely fatiguing so one thing I
always like to say is put a barbell on
your back and do step ups and put 70% of
your maximum leg strength on that step
up and just step up 12 in see how many
repetitions in a row you can do before
you get really tired well if walking up
a normal flight of
stairs requires Force production that is
equivalent to 70 or 80% of your maximum
leg strength that's how you're going to
feel every
day none of us want to be in that
position I don't need to really try to
encourage you more to to not want to be
uh specifically with your legs to be
weak upper body uh excellent research on
grip strength
being a a strong predictor of overall
longevity brain health Wellness I mean
you pick your metric here but just some
quick examples of why all of us really
should be paying attention to having a
sufficient amount as well as high
quality and high functioning skeletal
muscle now before we go too much further
I'd like to take a quick break and thank
our sponsors because they make this show
possible not only are they on this list
because they offer great products and
services but because I actually
personally love them and use them myself
today's episode is brought to by ran Ron
is a premium active wear company that is
easily my favorite in the world few
things have aggravated my wife more than
my clothing choices let's be honest
fashion is not exactly my strong suit
partially because I have just no sense
of style but also because I'm nurotic
about texture and feel there's not a
single brand I've tried over the years
that has the same quality feel and fit
that ran has absolutely mastered rone
uses best-in-class materials to allow
their products to be lightweight and
breathable but still durable and enough
to last even when you're training super
hard I remember the first time my wife
wore it for a cycling workout and she
who let's just say is uh well versed in
the active Weare world was genuinely
surprised by how soft and stretchy but
supportive the material was the Ron
women's collection actually just
launched and is already filled with
great reviews online the ran base
training shorts are brilliant as well
they fit perfectly and have the right
amount of stretch to allow total freedom
of movement they also have pockets which
I like and zippered Pockets that are
sneaky helpful for holding Hotel keys
and things like that the atmosphere tea
and commuter business shirts completely
blew my mind I do not understand how
they made this material I'll never go
back trust me here friends just stunning
craftsmanship all the way around if
you'd like to try ran go to ran spelled
RH ne.com perform to get 25% off your
first order again that's ron.com perform
to get 25% off your first order today's
episode is also brought to you by
Continuum Continuum is a membership only
wellness club designed to help high
performers reach their Fitness and
performance goals Continuum just opened
its Flagship Club in Manhattan quickly
making it one of the most sought-after
memberships in the city its location in
Greenwich Village is incredible in fact
it's stunning it's a 25,000 ft space
with state-of-the-art equipment a
beautiful design and everything you
could possibly want in this unique mix
of a gym Wellness Center and Social Club
Continuum members start with a thorough
Olympic grade assessment that results in
a biometrically driven AI assisted
wellness program that updates in real
time and incorporates everything from
personal training and physical therapy
to Hyperbaric and IV therapies by
bringing together true Fitness Experts
best-in-class technology and proven
Wellness services and amenities
Continuum delivers the most
comprehensive solution to Performance
I've been involved with Continuum
working as their head of performance
science since their founding and I've
been incredibly impressed by what the
team there has built if you're
interested in joining Continuum their
team has agreed to give a select number
of you the listeners here a fully waved
onboarding which includes V2 max testing
dexa scans blood panels sleep analysis
and more all at their Fabulous New York
City Flagship location to learn more
visit continuum. club/ perform again
that's Continuum with two use. club/
perform
okay as a very general overview when
we're talking about training for
hypertrophy we're typically looking at
something like 8 to 12 repetitions per
set now in the last 5 to eight years it
has become extremely clear hypertrophy
happens pretty equally from as low as
five repetitions per set all the way up
to 30 repetitions per set so you can go
anywhere in that window as long as
you're training to the same effort and
expect equal hypertrophy but that said
most of the time most most people stick
closer to kind of 8 to 12 repetitions
but by all means go lower or higher and
it should be no problem at all
absolutely equally effective what that
means then in terms of intensity is that
will Scale based upon how heavy you're
lifting generally if you're in the kind
of 8 to 12 repetition range you're
probably in the 70 to 80% of your one
rep max range if you were to go a little
bit lower say five six repetitions per
set you might be a little bit higher
higher maybe 80 85% and if you to go
lower in fact you can go as low as 30%
of your one repetition maximum that's
been shown extensively in the research
equally effective but that would just
require you to do 25 or 30 or
potentially even more repetitions per
set I've talked about the pros and cons
of this in other episodes and
potentially will even next season go
into the details um there are not the
same because of things like strength so
while you will expect equal
hypertrophy with say 25 repetitions per
set as would with eight repetitions per
set the strength progress will not be
the same strength needs to happen at a
lower rep range so that you can get the
intensity of the load high up typically
what we're looking at there is of course
what I've spoken of before the 3 to five
method so three to five repetitions per
set but that could go a little bit
higher um really do remember these are
not hard cut off lines these are just
kind of phased out so if I can get
strength at five repetition perc what do
you think happens at six still some
strength what about seven you still some
eight yeah sure but what about at 30
well okay very little and so what
happens is it's like it's just kind of
like where is the general place to be
most of the time that's all we're saying
with strength but because of what we're
trying to do reach a high load we have
to have a low repetitions per set
because fatigue starts to reduce the
amount of weight we can actually live so
strength is generally something again
like 3 to five rep repetitions plus or
minus can be as low as one if you want
to truly Peak strength you do one
repetition as heavy as you can there's
cons to that as well you want to go a
little bit higher five six seven reps
okay still fine but maybe you have to go
a little bit lighter gives you rough
context of what you're looking at for
power just continue that logic one more
step so because power has a strength and
velocity component not only can I not
afford to lose some Force output I can
afford to lose velocity either and so
power happens typically in a similar rep
range almost always the less than kind
of six reps per set at the most usually
even less than that right two to five
probably more so even than strength and
we have to do it at a fast speed so the
intensity the load can't be as high
because I have to move it fast okay so
while you could do something like this
say three sets of three repetitions at
95% of your bench press for strength
that's going to move very slow and so
that wouldn't be great at developing
power we would want to go to maybe three
sets of three repetitions at
65% so not super super light because now
we're just working on pure speed but not
super heavy either because now we're
just working on pure Force somewhere in
the middle every exercise has a
different optimal load in other words
how heavy you can lift what percentage
of your one rep max to maximize power
generally very generally upper body
smaller exercises tend to achieve their
Peak power at a lighter percentage 40%
of your max 50% of your max maybe as low
as 30% of your max bigger exercises like
a squat higher maybe 50% of your max 60%
of your max more complicated movements
like a snatch or a cleaning jerk can
even be as high as like 80 to 95% of
your one R Max so it does vary a little
bit but the point with power always is
it has to be a combination of heavy and
fast if it's fast and no load it's speed
but not power which is okay too if
that's what you're after if it's heavy
and very very slow it's Force which is
okay but it's not power either power
needs to be somewhere in the middle so
with that in mind then the rest range
for a
hypertrophy can really be whatever you'd
like it can be as small as 30 seconds
Now by doing that you're going to
accumulate more fatigue which means
you're either going to have to do less
repetitions or less weight or comination
but that's absolutely fine it can be
high rest even up to five minutes of
rest have been shown to produce equal
hypertrophy is 30 seconds obviously if
you go more rest you get more recovery
which means we now need to keep the
weight higher go higher and keep the rep
range higher or go higher and so pros
and cons there are subtle differences
but equal
benefit from short rest ranges as low as
30 seconds all the way up to longer rest
ranges up to 5 minutes for strength and
power though it's a different story you
need to stay away for the most part of
low res rals remember this is all about
quality we need to practice moving fast
a bunch of times we need to practice
moving heavy a bunch of times if we
shorten our rest rbls and we can't move
as fast we can't produce as much force
then we're not practicing producing
force and we're not practicing moving
faster and so we're really undercutting
our adaptations two to five minutes of
rest is the rough recommendation for
power and strength but you do want to
think about this in context if I were to
do say one vertical jump I don't truly
need to rest five minutes that's not
that fatiguing I could probably honestly
do one minute and be depending on how
fit you are you might even be able to do
like 40 seconds and be fine and so those
are they're just guidelines okay think
about the person think about what phase
of training they're in early in a
training phase maybe you want more rest
but 16 weeks into a training program
you're very fit you're very strong
you're in shape you maybe don't
necessarily need a full extensive rest
rval to produce Peak power again okay if
you're trying to maximize truly maximize
your strength you're probably going to
take five plus minutes of rest if you're
trying to work on a lot of different
repetitions on a lot of exercises of
power maybe 2 minutes is good five uh
often times when I say that people are
like oh my God five whole minutes and
they go to the gym they do it they start
their clock and like 30 seconds in
they're like oh my gosh like I have to
wait another four and a half minutes
well not necessarily all the time and
not and not for every exercise I will
caution
though you are not nearly as recovered
as you think you are if if you're used
to doing things that are like moderate
strength or hypertrophy or muscular
endurance you're not really
understanding and you typically can't
register what it feels like to be at
100% you get to kind of 90 92% and you
think yeah yeah I don't you don't feel
any difference in this particular case
if we're trying to maximize power and
strength that last 7% matters but you
may not be able to perceive it if you're
not used to it and so typically what id
say is if you're not used to this type
of training I would still take rest
intervals than you think you want to
what's the harm you cost yourself an
extra 6 minutes combined at the end of
the workout by doing 20 more seconds of
rest okay you can live with that okay if
eventually you realize that's enough and
you want to back a back down that's
great but initially start off with more
rest than you think for the most part
people error on the side of Too Short
when it comes to power and
strength not necessarily too long okay
so now that we're speaking the same
language about what we're going to get
into hypertrophy versus strength and
power we need to understand a few things
that are going to be true of both of
these programs and I want to say that
now so I don't have to repeat it twice
as we go through the individual programs
when we're talking about training for
muscle function we have to acknowledge a
few things one there are just a handful
of Concepts to go after but there are
infinite methods I'm simply going to
present to you a couple of them these
are scientifically validated and
supported as you'll hear later but
there's many many other scientifically
validated and supported methods for
hypertrophy and muscle strength so I
don't want you to think this is the only
way or necessarily even espousing this
is the single best approach because
that's not necessarily the case I just
know that these are effective and there
are many many other ways to go about
that depending on your context your
availability to exercise equipment your
background your goals your age your
sport you're participating in injury
history all of that would go into
designing your program I have any of
that context for you right now for this
individual program so I'm just going to
walk you through some highlights but
that is absolutely true these programs
are highly effective as I've experienced
personally but also there are many ways
to get to the same route that said when
we're talking about enhancing sport
performance that is clearly about more
than just muscle action so I tended
default to muscle because I'm a muscle
guy but I'm absolutely acknowledging
many things go into performing at your
best on the field field they on the
court or in the arena that's outside of
the scope of today but we will
acknowledge that even something as
simple as power so hitting a golf ball
farther or throwing a baseball harder
requires some muscle power but then you
have things like movement technique and
skill and timing and and all of these
allow you to perform better in your
sport to express more power in your
sport that don't necessarily require you
to enhance your functional ability in
the gym to produce more strength and
power so that is a little bit different
I'll acknowledge that but from this
perspective of let's just start at the
beginning all those conversations I just
said maybe we can have in future Seasons
but right now if I'm just trying to get
more powerful in the gym what would I do
this would be my answer so a few other
things you'll see consistent across both
these programs number one they are both
going to leverage a concept called
Progressive overload which means you
have got to overload the system in some
sort of systematic and intentional
fashion the easiest addage here is you
know add 5 pounds every week that
doesn't necessarily work I'm going to
talk through how we do that and even the
idea that you have to add load or weight
as your method of progressive overload
doesn't have to be the case in fact the
programs I'm going to share with you the
strength and power one does choose to
overload with uh intensity or weight but
the other one is actually keeping weight
somewhat consistent and overloading with
volume and that's because with
hypertrophy the primary driver of muscle
growth is going to be volume and so you
want to hold that most sacred if you go
up or down and sub weight it's not
nearly as important as it is that you
continually progress and overload your
volume strength and power are the
opposite though maintaining intensity
and the expression of force production
and power is more important than your
total volume typically and so you want
to hold that one more sacred and so I
actually picked these examples what's
nice about them is they are going to
follow in practice what the science
would also say about the physiology and
the mechanism that doesn't always happen
in fact quite often doesn't happen in
our world so it's really nice when we
see the science of mechanism and
Physiology line up perfectly with what
the experts are actually doing and that
ends up getting you the best real whole
world whole body performance outcomes
that are the best some other things
you'll notice both programs are heavy on
balance and what I mean by that is not
like your physical balance of tripping
and falling but balance of among the
programs so they do some work in in the
frontal sagittal and transverse planes
which means sort of up and down front
and back and rotation they're balancing
upper body and lower body left side and
right side they're balancing things like
um doing bilateral so two legs at a time
versus unilateral one leg at a time
they're balancing kettle bells and
dumbbells and barbells and bands and
sprinting and movement and they have
this General balance of equipment now
when I say balance I don't mean a
mathema iCal equal balance I'm just
meaning they're acknowledging and making
sure nothing's getting too squirly that
we're not doing 80% of our work on our
quads and 10% on our hamstrings or 80%
of our work on our upper body and 10% on
our
lower etc etc it's just a reasonable
balance and there's no specific numbers
behind that in fact they're different
among the programs but they're really
trying to pay attention to over the
course of these 8 to 12 weeks that we're
going to put somebody through of
intensified progressively overloaded
training we need to have a reasonable
balance between these different ways so
we're not creating asymmetries or even
maybe correcting some of the asymmetries
we have and we're keeping our joints
overall healthy that is probably the
most critical key component to training
and training harder over time while
staying healthy and injury-free so
progressing in an appropriate manner as
well as paying somewhat attention to
balance of the program last thing to
note here
and this is really true against any
exercise program for any goal is we have
to understand how we're modifying and
really be intentional and judicious
about all seven of the modifiable
variables if you've not heard that
phrase before I would recommend checking
out my guest series with Dr Andrew
hubman on the hubman Lab podcast I did
uh in 2023 we talked about them in
detail so to go through them quickly
here I use an acronym developed by my
former colleague and labmate Dr Lee
Brown which is called co-p It's a
Wonderful acronym scientists are always
great at developing acronyms but it
stands for Choice which is exercise
choice so what exercises are you
selecting this includes equipment as
well as what movement patterns and a lot
of things I just discussed a second ago
so the choice of the exercise you're
selecting influences in part what
adaptation you're going to get strength
and power or hypertrophy o which stands
for order it's another way of what order
do I do them in so what exercise goes
first in my day second third fourth
fifth Etc in the case of things like
strength and power order is incredibly
important you need to be hyp specific
with hypertrophy it's far less
important the next one is V for volume
this is how many repetitions multiplied
by how many sets throughout the week so
what's my total weekly or monthly volume
again as I said a second ago it's
important in both categories here that
we're paying attention but really we
need to make sure that we're not losing
volume over time with hypertrophy and
for strength we just want to make sure
we're not doing so much volume that is
compromising our ability to come back
and use high force and high power in our
next training session because those are
the ultimate drivers generally for those
adaptations the next is I for intensity
and that is refers to again what
percentage of your one repetition
maximum you're going after it's the
inverse answer to what I just said a
second ago where intensity needs to be
ke key for power and strength and where
it is important but far less relevant
for actual muscle hypertrophy F stands
for frequency this is how many days per
week easy distinction here when you're
training for hypertrophy you don't
necessarily want to train the same
muscle on multiple days in a row because
you need to allow some recovery now
where a lot of people actually make the
mistake here you don't need the muscles
to have complete rest it doesn't need to
be completely turned off for two or 3
days as you'll see in the program it's
not needed but you definitely don't want
to work it hard multiple days in a row
in your typical fashion strength and
power is the opposite you can train the
same muscles every single day as you'll
see the program does not a problem here
because there's not a lot of residual
fatigue not a lot of of local fatigue
rather like in the actual muscle not a
lot of soreness because we're not
pushing that adaptation and so frequency
can be very different between these two
programs and should be strength and
power requires practice which means more
repetition which me a lot more
frequenting R stands for rest which is
your rest interval how much time am I
taking between sets or even repetitions
you have the option for hypertrophy can
be low rest say 30 seconds of rest or
maybe even less all the way up to 5
minutes of rest but for strength and
power almost always you need to have a
minimum of three minutes of rest because
again we're going after something
different here this is really about the
quality of each individual movement and
so if we're keeping ourselves to a short
rest and we're losing our force or power
production then we're losing our actual
goal which means we're not going to get
what we're after there are exceptions to
all these rules but this is just a
standard default of typically what we're
trying to do the last variable here
stands for p progression which is how
are we progressing these things over
time and that is really what we're going
to talk about along the way so that said
that is kind of the fundamental
background of everything here and what
I'd like to do now is get into the two
programs I have intentionally selected
things as I mentioned earlier that I
have done personally I've done in my
actual self my training I've done them
with athletes I have coached and there
is research directly supporting them
you're going to see some of these in
fact one of the protocols is one I've
used in my laboratory for training
studies that we've completed so again I
know that these things work quite well
you're also going to notice that they're
both set up to be four days per week I
did that just to help you understand
both the training programs if you want
to modify them a little bit to 3 days a
week that is absolutely
possible that's something you'll have to
kind of figure out on your own if you
want to add increase this up to 5 days a
week that may be challenging but could
be done as well I would recommend though
if possible to do both these programs if
you're going to try them yourself really
do your best to try it at four days per
week you're going to get the best
results because that's intentionally and
specifically what they were designed for
I've also selected a couple of different
examples the hypertrophy one as you're
going to see is very straightforward I
wanted this to be pretty simple this
will be easy to listen to and be
something to uh to just really jump in
and try now neither of these programs
are easy they're going to have to work
hard as hard as you choose to but it's
it's again a little bit more
straightforward at the same token I
wanted to go over something more
advanced I know a lot of you listening
are at the beginning of your fitness
journey or have been coaching for a
little bit but some of you are at the
other end some of you are very very high
level coaches and so I wanted to to
provide some context of letting everyone
see this is what the strength training
stuff can look like um at a simple
straightforward that doesn't mean less
effective doesn't mean it doesn't work
as well but programs can be very simple
and they can be highly complicated and
both can work and that's really what I
want to highlight is the fact that just
because your program looks very simple
doesn't mean it won't work and just
because it looks really simple doesn't
mean it's actually any better either
absolutely rationale to make programs
very straightforward absolutely
rationale to make them far more
complicated entirely depends on the
context situation of both the client
you're working with as well as your
personal coaching abilities and skills
I'd like to take a quick break and thank
our sponsors today's episode is brought
to you by Renaissance periodization if
you want to put on muscle through
science-backed training programs look no
further than Renaissance periodization
RP as we call it in the industry guides
users through effective and easy to
follow lifting programs all through
their hypertrophy app these programs are
designed by the absolute best in the
industry including one of my my absolute
favorite sports scientist and
professional bodybuilder Dr Mike Israel
you may recognize that name because I've
referenced him and his work countless
times over the years so whether you're
looking to put on muscle gain strength
or both these programs will help you
achieve your goals and have produced
results in literally thousands of men
and women Renaissance periodization also
has a diet app that is backed by the
latest science and innovation in the
fields of nutrition and takes the
complexity out of dieting helping you
achieve your IDE body composition if
you'd like to try Renaissance
periodization go to rpstrength tocom
perform to save up to $50 off of your
subscription again that's rpst
strength.com perform to save up to $50
off your subscription today's episode is
also brought to you by momentus momentus
makes high quality nutritional and
dietary supplements I was deeply
skeptical of them as I am all supplement
companies given what I know about the
industry the low quality contamination
mislabeling and other issues plaguing
many companies in this space however I
was so impressed by what they're doing
and plan to do in the future that I
decided to not only bring them on as a
sponsor to the podcast but to formally
partner with them as well every single
one of their products is third- party
tested and 100% of their product line is
NSF or informed sport certified giving
you peace of mind that you're getting
exactly what they say you are so while
they offer excellent quality
foundational products such as Vitamin D
D greetin than fish oil they are also
highly Innovative having received 10 US
military Innovation and research grants
in recent years no supplement is
mandatory even the foundational ones
like the ones I just mentioned or their
grass-fed whey protein isolate are never
meant to replace or be used instead of
high quality food however they do have a
strong base of scientific support and
give you more options to hit your macro
and micronutrient targets for example I
personally found that the recovery
powder is fantastic for getting protein
carbohydrates magnesium and some
glutamine in without needing to give my
coaching clients a ton of directions or
several supplements to carry around if
you'd like to give it a try go to Liv
mous.com perform to get 20% off your
order again that's Liv mous.com perform
to get 20% off your order okay let's
dive into the programs the first program
I want to get into is the hypertrophy
one now this is designed to be 8 weeks
and is something we used in my
laboratory for an actual real training
study I can't go over and tell you which
study we used it for because it's
currently in review but what I can tell
you is without question it worked it
worked for muscle size the people
actually got a lot stronger too as I
said earlier when you add muscle you're
almost surely going to add some strength
unless you're at the very end of that
Spectrum you're a very high level
bodybuilder where you might add some
muscle and not see a lot of functional
gains and strength most people that add
a sufficient amount of muscle in the
appropriate way are going to add a lot
of strength and these folks did as well
we also had them specifically because
this was actually a nutrition based
study on a hypercaloric diet so we were
controlling for um their nutrition and
their training and and everything else
there so a lot of context went into this
but this program absolutely works and we
put it into practice this was led by
three of of my fantastic graduate
students Co Cody uh Chelsea and Danny
all of whom have gone on to be excellent
very high level coaches themselves so a
lot of confidence in the quality of this
program fin important note it was built
directly by a gentleman named meno
henselman meno has a master's degree in
the field he is a highly published
scientist as well so he collaborated
with us on this program so this is
actually developed by meno um his
website is meno hl.com a really
highlevel personal trainer strength
coach worked with tons of people in the
past and is wonderful with education so
if you like to learn about this stuff he
has courses excellent social media so
Mano is a great person for
evidence-based personal training and
strength conditioning so men built this
program so wanted to make sure he got
due credit for that because he just gave
it to us and we plugged it in and played
and it worked wonderfully well so um
thank you for that meno and let's go
ahead and get into it the way the
program was constructed was to use what
we call an ABAB model which is to say
it's four days a week and you basically
repeat the exact same day twice every
other day so a on Monday repeated a On
th Thursday B on Tuesday is repeated B
on Friday it's not necessarily an upper
lower split if you're familiar with that
term because you're doing really upper
and lower body every single day now I
like the fact that we kept the two days
identical if you need more variation in
your life you can do that but it is
actually quite nice scientifically to
have the same day repeated twice per
week because we can control and monitor
and measure volume intensity and a bunch
of other variables it's also easier to
coach because we don't have to teach
twice as many exercises so a strong
value proposition to this is it's simple
easy to explain and your body will
become incredibly customed to the
workouts because you're doing the same
workout twice per week it doesn't
necessarily have to go Monday Tuesday
Thursday Friday like we did in our lab
per se but that would be the typical
approach that way the workout from
Monday you're resting on Tuesday you're
resting on Wednesday and then coming
back and doing it again Thursday the
same basic idea for the Tuesday and
Friday approach and then you've got the
two days in the weekend to fully recover
so just just the way again if you want
to do it a little bit differently if you
wanted to take two days in between and
then come back that's fine but that
that's entirely up to you it was also
built on a methodology which is really
common and quite popular these days
called Auto regulation been a bunch of
research on it it is highly effective a
handful of metaanalyses and uh review
articles have been published in the last
few years on it it is somewhat newer
though now Auto regulation has been
around for a very long long time but the
scientific research on it really has
been around for the last you know 10
years or so and it is quite effective
what this means is instead of
pre-programming out exactly how heavy
you're going to lift and how many
repetitions you do you let your body's
response guide us a little bit that's
why it's called Auto regulation so we're
regulating the intensity and the volume
based on how your body is responding
rather than a pre-planned number okay
it's actually quite simple but this is a
nice blend of having a structure in a
plan while also letting your body
respond to it and this allows you to be
individualized and so instead of me
putting everyone in the entire study on
the exact same program knowing that it
wouldn't be enough volume for some
people it'd be way too much volume for
others and then there'd be a bell curve
in the Middle where it's okay I want to
maximize my response in everybody just
like you I want all of you to get the
best results and I can't give you exact
numbers without knowing any of you and
so the better way is to let your body
respond and see what's actually
happening and those of you that need
less volume will see that your body is
asking for more of a back off those of
you need more volume will see the
opposite and those that this is perfect
for you'll know exactly what that means
so how this operates is every set we ask
you to do the most amount of repetitions
possible at the given weight if you can
do two or more repetitions more than the
set requires then we actually increase
the weight by 2 and a half% so let's say
ask you do to do a set of 10 repetitions
and you do 12 repetitions you've done
two more than what we planned therefore
the next set we increase the weight by
2.5% if you could do two or less than
the requirement or what we asked you to
do so in this case we asked you to do 10
and you only did eight then we dro the
load by 10% so we take that off and we
do that for every single set for every
day for every single week and so
depending on if you're getting really
tired and you start executing less
repetitions then we're going to start
backing the weight off and if we back
the weight off and you still can't get
10 repetitions we back it off even more
but if you're responding even if you're
sore tired but your body is executing
and Performing then we can continue to
add and how do we know that we added too
much well because then your repetitions
would go down too much and so we are
really seeing what happens we know
exactly what you did last week we came
back in we start there if you did you
know again more than two repetitions
above the plan or less than two
repetitions we either add 2 and half% of
load or reduce 10% now for the most part
we're working on you know 5 to 10 pound
increments we don't have always
necessarily access to one pound plates
and so this isn't going to be perfect do
the best thing you can if you can get to
2 and A2 pound increments that's great
but a lot of times most people are going
to be working on 5 to 10 PBS so don't
get overly specific about that 2 and a
half% and 10% just do the best you
possibly can all right so what this
actually specifically looked like in our
program here's the following workout
remember there's just an A and A B
workout but you would repeat a and You'
Repeat b twice during the week so the a
workout was a Romanian deadlift four
sets of 8 to 12
repetitions all of these would have uh
for the most part three minute rests by
the way and so just as a very specific
example you would warm up for all this
stuff every single day has a a basic
obic warmup it has a specific warm-up so
uh you may do two or three sets of
Romanian deadlifts to kind of build up
to your load here we would never just
start you at you know say 100 pounds
with the most amount of reps you can do
is your very first set for the day so
all that is going to be taken care of
and when you're really actually truly
ready to get to what we call a working
set this is when this Auto regulation
part starts all right so let's just say
this very first week the very first set
of Romanian deadlifts we did 100 lb
for we said 8 to 12 repetitions and you
got 10 repetitions done great we'll
leave you at 100 and now the next set
you got nine
repetitions great we leave you at 100
now the next set you got seven
repetitions okay well now since you've
done less than two two less than what we
wanted we're going to reduce that load
by 10% so we'll take 10 pounds off and
see how many reps you can do for your
fourth and final set that's the basic
idea right so that day four sets of 8 to
12 rdls remaining
deadlifts five sets of leg extensions at
8 to 12 reps barbell bench press for
four sets 6 to 10 reps there neutral
grip pull down for four sets of 8 to 12
seated calf raay for five sets of 8 to2
and then finally cable lateral raises
for three sets of 8 to 12 those last two
exercises would be at 2 minutes rest
rather than but everything else would be
at the 3 minutes rest in addition want
to add some context this was
specifically designed for whole body
hypertrophy but also we did make sure
that there was specific exercises on the
muscles that we were measuring and so we
were using an ultrasound and other
tactics to measure direct muscle gain
and so if you're wondering why we chose
some muscle groups over the other it was
just to do a whole body workout you
can't do every single thing and we
wanted to make sure we were targeting
the muscles in this case especially the
vasis lateralis and the quadricep muscle
to ensure they directly were getting
Activation so if you see things like the
leg extension being the second exercise
for the day and you think well why
didn't we do a a back squat or front
squat or something like that is we just
scientifically wanted to ensure without
question that the quads directly got
activated so we did that very first so
typically you wouldn't do a single joint
exercise like a leg extension prior to
doing U your bigger mole multi-joint
exercises but there's also a thing about
exercise order that says do the thing
that's most important first and so we
did that really early on to ensure we
got the quads and if this means we lost
a little bit of performance in our
seated calf raises or something that's
fine because it wasn't the primary
muscle of interest to be as clear as
possible here when we say if they have
two or more or two or less repetitions
outside the range what I'm talking about
is outside that range and so as you you
see the repetition range for the
exercises was 8 to 12 6 to 10 Etc so in
this particular case if the range was 8
to 12 we would need them to do two or
more outside of that range so two or
more over 12 so 14 or two or more less
than the bottom of the range eight so
they have to do six or more before we
start changing the loads so um you it's
going to be really hard always to get an
exact repetition number and that's why
we usually work within a range it's also
because we know that hypertrophy is very
well stimulated in 8 to 12 repetitions
it's also stimulated in other repetition
ranges but to make sure we still stayed
most of our time in a really highly uh
productive and effective repetition
range that's kind of where we we landed
them 8 to 12 and if they got below that
we're probably getting excessive fatigue
and above that it may not be enough load
to maximize mechanical tension and we
wanted to make sure we did that cuz
we're trying to maximize muscle growth
now the B workout was very similar first
exercise there was a high bar squat four
sets of 5 to eight repetitions there now
I don't know I could ask meno this but
my assumption is the reason why we went
to five to eight repetitions there as
opposed to 8 to 12 is when you add that
kind of fatigue to a complex Movement
Like A Barbo squat now you're talking
about multiple joints that are involved
you're talking about a load on your back
which compromises and restricts
breathing the fatigue associated with
something like a high bar squat relative
to a leg extension is unexplainably
higher and so a couple of reasons
probably behind that but that alone is
probably why we kept that a little bit
lower um doing as many reps as possible
for five four to five sets of 8 to 12
repetitions is insanely gnarly for an
exercise like a back squat in addition
uh you've got other issues and concerns
with safety and technique and stuff like
that so that's probably my my reason why
now actually on that note I want to say
one more thing that I forgot to say at
the beginning and that is as a part of
our Auto regulation technique counts and
so when we're saying if they did less
than two repetitions outside of the
range or more than the failure point is
technique the failure point is not them
racking the bar out but if they see a
change in Technique we count that as a
failure it's never a reason or allowed
for us to try really really hard where
we have a combination of kind of heavy
load and a lot of fatigue and then allow
repeated breakdowns of technique and so
that is what we're looking for a break
of technique represents failure it's not
necessarily just explicit direct
muscular failure it's if you break
position you have a more than a very
moderate or very mild uh breakdown in
technique then you're considered to be
failed okay so the B workout High bar
back squats uh four sets of 5 to eight
repetitions lying leg curls five sets of
8 to 12 repetitions barbell overhead
press three sets of 6 to 10 seated
Rose three sets of 8 to 12 cable chest
fly five sets of 6 to 10 triceps push
down two sets of 8 to 12 and then
finally seated dumbbell curls two sets
of 8 to 12 repetitions now those last
two exercises like we did on the a day
as well those last two tricep push down
and seated dumbbell curls we're at 2
minutes of rest rather than three as I
mentioned earlier the training program
did work in our particular study
important to note our uh participants
were young so these were College
individuals they were men and women and
they were very highly trained so the
results are going to be different if you
go into different scenarios however if
you look across the research landscape
you'll see that this style is an
effective method now just to give you
some context and results whenever we
analyze uh study participants in
training programs we're looking how
every individual person responds because
we we know some people will be
hyperresponders others will be
non-responders and so it's important to
understand each one of you if you were
to actually get this program and do it
yourself there's going to be a range in
responsiveness so I will just share with
you kind of the group averages but it is
important to acknowledge that again very
results May Vary if you will so just
going over some some of the basic things
now our participants got a lot stronger
their squat uh maximum strength their
one rep max increased by about 133%
again just a rough average there some
more some less some quite a bit more
some quite a bit less and and there was
other interventions going on in the
study um and that there are differences
but as a general answer it worked quite
a bit um raw numbers here you're going
to see something like a 14 and a half
kilo increase in strength which would be
about a 32 pound Improvement or
something over the course of8 weeks
which is quite a lot especially
considering it wasn't a program designed
to optimize strength bench press is a
similar story about a 10% Improvement
collectively across both wings of the
study and men and women about an 8 kilo
jump and performance which is about 172
lbs muscular endurance we tested this in
a number of different ways so not uh to
confuse you but you can kind of think of
that that improved by 13 to 16% or so so
your ability to perform multiple
repetitions at a given sub maximum load
went up that should make the most sense
because if you're thinking back to the
style of training we did where we asked
them to do as many repetitions as
possible every single single set we were
we were training them for this test is
one way to think about it now not
directly but indirectly so how many
repetitions can you do at a given weight
then you had a similar training style so
not surprised that they had a very large
response there in both their legs and
arms uh and again across all the groups
there they also improved muscle size um
so you're talking about a group average
of 1.8 kilos or more which is about 4
lbs U which was again quite impressive
represented you know ballp part about a
3% Improvement but that's really hard to
interpret because you had pretty big men
and pretty small women all combined
together and so wouldn't be concerned so
much about the uh actual percent change
there because that might sound low to
you but the fact that fairly trained
folks put on an average of four pounds
of muscle in8 weeks is a pretty
impressive response and I think is
realistic um so you would expect not
much more than that but less than that
also would be maybe concerning so
probably a pretty good number number
that does suggest a very reasonable but
effective program The Next program I
want to cover is designed to maximize
strength and power I'll explain a little
more of the context and walk you through
it in one second but I do want to
reiterate it's best if you get this
thing and follow along with me if you
really do want to learn because while
the previous program was pretty easy to
digest uh just listening or watching
here this one is more complicated and
I'll do my best to kind of walk you
through the concepts and give you a
couple of samples but it is a 4-day week
program that has three different phases
over 12 weeks and multiple subcomponents
to each phase and so just that alone is
going to let you know that I can't walk
you through the entire program because
it is complicated and changes every
single week where the previous program
it was the same exercises all throughout
the eight weeks so we don't have to
worry about that and really it was a
two-day week program that you double
this is not the case so we'll do my best
to highlight the big picture why the
coach designed it the way he did and
then give a couple of sample days and
some progressions but you'll really will
need to get the full thing to see it
more as I mentioned the program was
developed really for a an athlete this
is assuming you're in kind of a
preseason phase so you've got 12 weeks
or three months prior to competition and
it finishes with a taper so it's a D Lo
and it kind of backs you down so that
you could roll right into performance
this was developed and built by a friend
of mine named Travis Mash Travis Mash
has a master's degree in the field as
well I believe he's working on his PhD
now he has over 20 years of experience
coaching athletes in a number of sports
including NFL players a number of
Olympians across multiple Sports Travis
himself is one of the most legendary and
famous powerlifters of all time I think
he still holds world records in the
total he competed mostly in the 220
pound weight class I think his best
total I'm look at
2414 lbs uh this was a 970 lb squat and
remember at 220 lbs so almost in the
neighborhood of you know four and a half
to getting close to 5x body weight of a
squat so 970 lb squat 705 lb bench press
76611 for you there Trav pound deadlift
for a total of again
2,414 lb which I believe is still an
all-time record to this day so Travis
himself is a practitioner H he has
multiple athletes he's getting ready
that will likely qualify and compete in
the Paris o Olympics and the sport of
weightlifting and is extremely decorated
I could go on and on about Travis uh but
coach tons of people from youth to
college to these high level ones so
really designed this uh program with
this in mind also uses a concept similar
to Auto regulation so you'll see hints
and twinges of that as well but a set up
based on how many repetitions you can
complete it is based on how fast you can
complete so he uses a method called
velocity Based training
lots of research in the last decade on
vbt uh for short and so it's a similar
idea which to say instead of us
pre-programming and using entirely
repetitions and sets and loads that we
think you know 6 weeks in advance will
work it is saying how your body responds
and adjusting to what's actually
happening but instead of adjusting it by
your muscular endurance or repetitions
it is by the actual velocity you achieve
on the barbell so how fast can you move
that load if you're too slow we change
things if you're too fast we change
things so Auto regulation but again by
velocity in large part there's a large
component of it that is pre-programmed
and pre pre- delivered using a concept
that I've talked about in other places
called the pipin chart so basically says
how many total repetitions should you
accomplish at 60 to 70% 70 to 80 90 to
90 plus percent Etc so that is all baked
in as well so it's a combination of
Travis's powerlifting and Olympic
weightlifting background as well as his
work with field sport athletes and
really Blends it all together under this
Auto regulation velocity Based training
approach to make sure that you are
getting stronger getting faster and then
moving better last little part here is
that you'll see this program actually
involves a lot of onfield movement so
there's acceleration and change of
direction there's Sprint work there's
agility work there's Plyometrics and so
this is really a nice comprehensive
program
to develop an athlete particularly a
field or court or pitch-based athlete uh
for a pre for an actual going into a
season phase and it is pretty
comprehensive in that fashion so the
workouts are highly effective and what
they typically will do is use a style of
programming where we address multiple
different variables in the exact same
workout so as a concept and we'll get
into this in a second we're not going to
just do say strength in one day or
hypertrophy in one day
if we need to do strength and
hypertrophy we'll do them both in the
same day but depending on how much of an
emphasis we want to place on one over
the other we will alter the amount of
time we spend so for example if we want
to just do a little bit of speed work we
might do one speed drill for two or
three sets and then we want to have a
big strength component we might do three
or four strength exercises and then we
want to do just a little bit of muscular
endurance at the end there might be one
muscular endurance in a different phase
when we want to emphasize speed more
maybe we still do that speed strength
and muscular endurance component but now
we take 3/4 of the strength movements
away and replace those with an extra
three or four speed components and so
we're doing a lot of different things
speed acceleration change of Direction
High Velocity low velocity Ecentric
muscular endurance muscle Health like
all kinds of things and we're almost
always doing it all in one day but we
may only do literally one exercise or a
couple of sets for each thing now this
is important and uh used a lot in this
style of training because they need to
be able to make sure that we don't say
go five or six weeks without training a
particular style or component think of
it this way imagine you're going into
season and you spent eight weeks focused
on hypertrophy you did the program I
talked about earlier and that's great
you got a little bit stronger you add a
lot of muscle and that's awesome but
you're a soccer player you play lacrosse
okay you haven't moved yet you haven't
CH you haven't done any change of
Direction you haven't gotten faster you
haven't jumped you haven't put put your
body in weird position you've just
gained muscle size and some strength now
we switch over and we start doing things
like on the field we're doing agility
drills we're we're doing cleans and
throwing medicine balls well if we do
that exclusively for the next 12 weeks
by the time we get six 8 10 weeks in
it's now been two and a half months
since we've done any hypertrophy work so
what do you think happens to all that
hypertrophy we spent so much time and we
worked so hard to achieve two and a half
months ago
a lot of it goes away and so for an
athlete who needs to have multiple
components as I mentioned you need to be
fast you need to have acceleration Peak
velocity those are different components
of speed you need muscular strength
connected tissue Health you need
muscular endurance you need size you
need all these things instead of just
doing one at a time in these big eight
or 10 week chunks and then not seeing
the same type of adaptation again for
the next 8 to 10 weeks you do a little
bit of it every day enough to just keep
it stimulated to keep it alive but then
you change your emphasis and your focus
on another component as you go from week
to week to week so before we jump into
the actual details here a couple of
final reminders again the program is
available on a PDF in the show notes in
its entirety and Travis as well has a
ton of education on this program as well
as others on his website Mash elite.com
Travis is exceptional with his education
on his social media and podcasts uh lots
of free stuff there so tons of other
programs you can get from Travis so I
would encourage you to to go to all of
those before you get here with this
particular program as I just laid out
there are multiple components and so the
workouts are a little bit longer you're
going to be asked to rest a lot
maximally almost 3 minutes plus between
most of your sets and so they do extend
uh into a little bit longer period of
time if you are not an athlete and
you're listening to this and you're like
I want to get stronger and more powerful
but I don't have 90 minutes for my
workout you might have to modify
something like this you may have to take
out entire components you may reduce it
to 3 days a week or spread it out and so
absolutely there can be some
modifications and they should be but
these workouts candidly will take you a
little bit longer because you're not
only strength training but you're also
doing your field work and you're doing
things that would be typically done even
sometimes across multiple workouts in a
day for an athlete and that would be
fairly standard but I would admit not
necessarily applicable for the the
non-athlete uh folks that are out there
listening so uh keep that in context
however we're not spending a full
workout on each subcomponent for example
if we're doing power we might do one
exercise for two sets for power that's
not going to take very long that's a
five minutes and we're rolling on our
next one so you can actually get four
five or six different components of
training done in a single day and not
have it be two and a half hours in fact
I I could say the same would be true for
the hyper training program you even if
you do three or four exercises in a day
and you're just focusing on hypertrophy
if you do enough sets that could easily
end up being a two-hour workout and
anyone who's trained a lot for muscle
growth can certainly attest the fact
that it is not crazy to do a 90 plus
minute workout and I would see this to
be no different so can be shorter but
candid probably going to be fairly long
because you're trying to get a specific
outcome and you're training for a lot of
different things to make you the best
athlete possible I'd like to take a
quick break and thank our sponsors
today's episode is brought to you by a
AG G1 ag1 is a foundational nutrition
greens supplement that means ag1
provides a variety of vitamins minerals
probiotics prebiotics and adaptogens in
an easy to drink greens powder initially
I was very skeptical of ag1 as I am with
all supplement companies frankly but
after months of discussions with their
lead nutrition scientists and the team
at ag1 I've been impressed by their
commitment to sourcing the highest
quality ingredients and rigorous testing
to ensure that every single batch is
free of ban substances allergens heavy
metals microbes pesticides herbicides
residual solvents and microt toxins it's
even earn the prestigious NSF certified
for sport third-party testing approval
now ag1 is not a replacement for eating
Whole Foods but it is a great way to
fill in the gaps and it's been a big
help pushing some of my clients just in
the right direction for eating more
highquality Foods because it helps them
with Cravings digestion and many other
benefits now not everyone needs to
consume greens powders but if you're
going to do so you better make sure it
actually includes the ingredients that
it claims to and that those ingredients
are of the best sourcing if you'd like
to try ag1 you can go to drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 again that's drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus G2 today's episode is also brought
to you by Maui Nei venison Maui Nei
venison is my absolute favorite thing to
eat period it's beyond delicious and the
highest protein per calorie meat you
will find Maui venison is 100% wild
harvested meat not fenced farmed or fed
in any way the venison is ethically and
sustainably hunted on the island of Maui
and is far beyond the quality of any
beef grass-fed or whatever you've ever
tried in your life and I know cuz I grew
up in the country and I've tried it all
it's easy to cook and tastes incredible
my wife and small kids absolutely inhale
it and the jerky sticks are a daily
staple for me with 10 g of protein and
just 55 calories while Maui Nei venison
offers the highest quality meat
available there is a catch supplies are
limited by Nature responsible population
management means they won't go beyond
the Harvest capacity memberships are the
best way to ensure that you can get the
meat you want whenever you want it so be
sure to secure your spot now Maui new
venison is offering perform listeners
20% off their first purchase of jerky
sticks fresh Venison and bone broth
while supplies last the bone broth by
the way has 25 g of protein in it itself
visit mauii venison docomo for 20% off
okay so what's this program look like 12
weeks long and it's going to go through
three specific phases four days a week
for the entire 12 weeks and it uses a
style of periodization called Block
periodization it's been around since
probably the 1960s but has gotten much
more popular in the last 25 years or so
and for a number of reasons but one of
them being one of the biggest proponents
of it a gentleman by the name of Dr
Vladimir yiran a Russian scientist who's
been around this world for a very long
time and has produced a number of
Publications uh using block
periodization so you can read more about
his work we'll certainly put a number of
those instrumental papers available as a
PDF in the show notes but a lot of work
from Vladimir and his group in this area
also been directly applied to tons of of
athletes and a lot of different sports
and contexts and is very effective and
so really with block periodization there
are three fundamental phases we want you
to go through they're called
accumulation
transmutation and
realization what this really means is
we're typically looking at one to four
weeks per phase so in this particular
case four weeks of accumulation four
weeks of transmutation and four weeks of
realization accumulation is what it sort
of sounds like you're going to
accumulate money in the bank if you will
so you're making deposits that we're
going to cash out later you're
accumulating volume you're building up
fatigue in the system on purpose you're
overloading and overreaching the body so
that we can get results later now once
you've done that you're going to
transmute it you're going to transfer it
so you're going to take let's say your
new found muscular size and strength and
try to translate that into power and
speed and Ecentric control and you're
going to transmute it into what specific
things you want now one of the reasons
this style of programming becomes so
popular among strength editioning
coaches is it allows you to be specific
at this phase so we can be General with
accumulation and now be super specific
by transmuting your adaptations for a
discus thrower and transmuting it
slightly differently for a wrestler and
transmuting it slightly differently for
a high jumper all right and so we're
transmitting into more specific fashion
the last phase is realization where you
start to Peak right you start to realize
the benefits you start to actually get
faster jump higher hit the tennis ball
harder and all those things so we're
building up volume we're transmitting it
transferring it into the exact output we
want and then we're realizing it peing
and tapering at the end at the highest
level the way that we accomplish that is
if you think about three primary
variables volume specificity and
intensity volume is repetitions
multiplied by your set intensity is you
know what percentage of your one rep max
or maximum speed or maximum heart rate
you know how hard are you working and
then specificity how specific are you to
the actual thing you want to get done so
again for a volleyball player you'll
want to think about things like vertical
jump okay that's really specific to a
volleyball player that's not necessarily
as specific as something like a 100
meter Sprinter yes they want to be able
to jump high but really they want to be
able to run horizontally as fast as
possible so at the very beginning in
this first accumulation phase
your volume is the highest and as you go
from accumulation to transmutation to
realization your volume comes down in
all three of those intensity does
basically the opposite so the very first
phase high volume low intensity the next
phase volume comes down intensity goes
up the last phase volume goes way down
intensity comes way up if you think
about this from the field Sport and I
know I'm using a lot of sport athlete
analogies but remember the same concepts
are true whether you're an athlete or
not as we get closer to wanting to have
our Peak you want to be producing the
most speed power strength however you're
going to express these new found
physical capabilities and you don't want
to be fatigued though volume drives
fatigue so we reduce the volume we
increase the intensity so you go your
fastest prior to having to go fast you
produce your most power prior to needing
to actually produce your power on the
field or on the court specificity
continues to go up so it's very general
at the very beginning gets more specific
in the second phase and then specificity
really takes off during the last phase
this could come in a number of different
areas Energy Systems range of motion
type of exercise uh the uniform you put
on as easy examples maybe you start off
on machines at the very beginning which
are not very similar to what you would
be doing on an ice hockey rink right you
would when you're playing I ice hockey
you're on skates you're unbalanced your
feet aren in the same position and in a
machine you take all that away but
you're trying to be General here just as
an example and then maybe the next phase
you move in off of a machine onto
dumbbells and then the Final Phase you
move off from dumbbells onto maybe an
unstable surface that not necessarily to
say that that's a great way but you get
the point you're moving from General
stuff into more and more specific things
as we get closer to competition so
that's how we're going to play with all
those variables as a general example of
the philosophy of block periodization
works with all that background I'd like
to walk you through how Travis has set
up these different weeks we're going to
start off with just the accumulation
phase I'm going to show you how he's
built day one day two day three day four
and how we're going to change goals
slightly after this we'll go through
transmutation and then finally
realization along the way and at the end
I I'll give you more but I'll give you
specific examples of the exact days as
well as and I think this is important
for a lot of people
how Travis progresses from say day one
week one to day one week 2 to day one
week three Etc so how are we going from
Monday to Tuesday but also how we going
from Monday week one to Monday week two
to Monday week three what small changes
are we making how are we progressing
intensity how are we managing volume I
can't cover all of it you can run the
grid there right uh many different sub
goals four days a week 12 day that's a
big Matrix that need to cover so I'll
just pick out a couple key examples that
I think are the best way to represent
what Travis is doing overall but the
final details will just be in that PDF
in the show notes so getting us started
phase one is accumulation now in this
particular phase very first day the
overall focus is acceleration and lower
body rate of force development as well
as some hypertrophy so again you can see
there's multiple components there and
what I also love about this style of
programming is Travis tells the athlet
specifically
what the big goal is a lot of people
jump in they just want to know the
exercise of the Reps and that's
important but let the athlete or client
and yourself know what are we trying to
do we're trying to move fast today we're
trying to accelerate today we're trying
to do Max Speed we're trying to do a
little bit of this it's incredibly
effective to let them know because when
questions pop up they run short on time
the exercise isn't available maybe
something's hurt if they're just
following the program they may not
necessarily know what to say okay you
know what the primary goal today day was
in this particular case acceleration so
while I don't have this piece of
equipment I know a good substitute is
anything I can do where I can still
accelerate something that blocks my
acceleration but is maybe good for
strength wouldn't be a great switch out
here because I know I'm trying to go
after acceleration if that piece is gone
and they're just seeing a speed movement
they don't necessarily know what you're
trying to get at and so they can't
necessarily make changes so I love the
fact that we're telling them what's the
outcome goal we're after and in this
particular case you got three of them on
this particular day he's got four
subcomponents now I probably should have
said this at the beginning but every
single day no matter what phase or what
week we're in there's always an
extremely long high quality Dynamic
warm-up right uh so I'll go through one
example of that but just plant that in
your head as that is incredibly
important to this process especially
because we're going to start these
workouts asking you to go as fast as
possible we need to make sure your
neurological system your muscular system
and mental
you're ready to actually move fast so
there are long and very specific
warm-ups and these warm-ups do differ
from dayto Day based on the movement
patterns needed in that day as a quick
example if you're going to be sprinting
more that day there's probably going to
be more of a focus on making sure the
hamstrings and the calves and the feet
are really warmed up if there is maybe
some speed work but maybe a large focus
on strength then the hips are going to
be nice and open up and the back are
going to be activated and we want all
those things for everything but you see
the point where we're just emphasizing
something slightly more or less based on
what we know we're going to ask them to
do in a few more minutes and so to going
back to it we've got the four components
for this particular day Dynamic warmup
and then it's going to be acceleration
in this particular case it's going to be
sprinting acceleration second component
is power or power development the third
is what's going to be kind of combined
together as strength hypertrophy and
rotational power and then the fourth is
knee health for Speed now in that Travis
is specifically saying when we start
going fast I know knee injuries T
injuries tend to pop up and so we're
going to go ahead that call this
prehabilitation if you'd like and we're
going to start working on knee Health in
a specific way where the knee can start
to brace High movement and control so
that when we get into knee uh speed
stuff later our knees are actually nice
and healthy day two is a little bit of a
different overall Focus now it is
athlete specific hypertrophy meaning
maybe one athlete needs more size in
their quad another needs more in their
glutes or hamstrings or whatever it may
be so it's different amounts of hyper
work specific to the athlete as well as
change of Direction what Travis is also
doing here as you notice and most you'll
see when we get to the exercises you're
going to be working full body every day
but by changing the emphasis slightly so
we're not doing hypertrophy necessarily
every day we're not necessarily doing
agility or we do agility one day or
change the direction and then full
sprinting the next day so we have enough
variation in our movement well we're
we're still working the same muscles but
we're asking the joint and the movement
patterns to be so different our
likelihood of overuse just general
strain goes down pretty low and so we
can allow us to do more stuff more
frequently at a higher intensity by
having variations in the movement
patterns so overall emphasis again for
the day athlet specific hypertrophy as
well as change of Direction Four
subcomponents within that we've got our
Dynamic warmup of course rotation and
change of Direction to start off with
then we go into posture supporting
strength you can probably imagine what
that type of stuff is third component is
strength for High Velocity
Force if you dive into this world deeply
which we're not going to have time to
get into today force is not just one
thing power is not just one thing
velocity is not just one thing there's a
spectrum within that and so Travis is at
the level and this program is designed
to be at a level where we're actually
going to be nitpicking different areas
of that Force curve different areas of
the Velocity curve and then different
areas of the force velocity curve on top
of that I told you it can get very very
very Advanced and complicated and I
wouldn't say that this program is overly
complicated but it is very well thought
through to make sure we're hitting all
components of speed agility acceleration
Peak velocity Etc so that's what he
means when he says strength for High
Velocity Force so this is a little bit
of force but at a high velocity okay
fourth and final component for that day
is hypertrophy for course symmetry so
this would simply be looking at again as
your anterior side much larger than your
posterior side so the front maybe your
front shoulder is much bigger than your
posterior deltoid so we would then do
hypertrophy to clean up that asymmetry
maybe your right side's bigger than your
left side or whatever the case may be so
nice little component
there again as clear examples that
hypertrophy for symmetry as we'll see in
a second might be a couple of sets of
one
exercise but the majority of our day
we're going to be spent on part one
which is our rotation change of
Direction so we can do small amounts of
everything here to not and not still
really make this an incredibly high
volume fatiguing or even really that
long of a workout day three is an
athletic speed development as well as a
lower high velocity strength day now I
know that's a little bit wordy but it'll
actually make sense when you see the
program four components here going to be
our Pure speed stuff at the very
beginning then power then strength for
High Velocity Force production and then
finally back to knee health for Speed so
we've gotten that in twice already in
our week fourth and final day is maximum
speed and upper High Velocity strength
so upper body High Velocity strength do
speed right at the beginning to get us
going there we'll work on concurrent
power which is a different style of
power athletic strength and then finally
transmutation uh using a giant set for
our upper body development this is
hypertrophy kind of for the upper body
but we're going to be transmuting a
little bit into the next phase already
what he's kind of doing there is saying
we know what we're going to get to in
the next phase so I need to set it up
right now so we can actually get to that
work when we get there and it we're not
you know unsupported for that so that's
the overlay of that first phase before
we go on to transmutation let's go over
some examples right now you got four
different specific warm-up patterns but
let me just give you a couple so you can
see I'm not going to do this for the
next two phases so I want to tackle warm
up a little more detail right now and
then we'll skip past it a little bit
later but just want to give you some
exact repetitions and exercises to help
you understand so remember what we're
talking about here is day one we're
focusing globally for day one on
acceleration and lower body rate of
force development so not only developing
you know High Force production but doing
it as fast as possible as well as
hypertrophy okay the dynamic warmup for
that day is going to focus on getting
actually warmed up for the rest of the
workout as well as laying the groundwork
for acceleration so all that context
this is what we're working on starting
off with something like a walking lunges
for 10
repetitions that's it 10 reps of a
walking lunge one set then we're going
to go to unilateral standing hip
abduction so you can imagine standing up
and raising your leg out and away from
you so AB adduction it a deduction is a
you know like ad where you bring your
leg back to the midline you're adding to
the midline a b duction is you're taking
away so you're raising your leg outside
so like the outside of your hip is kind
of controlling pulling your leg out to
an uh uh out to the side of you you do
that for eight repetitions then you move
on to a side lunge for another eight
repetitions then a a quadruped so on
your hands and knees position and you're
going to do some hip
mobilization working on the front the
the anterior and posterior side for
about 30 seconds then moving into
intentional hip internal rotation so
kind of like a a fire hydrons and hip
circles if you will moving that stuff
around and you're going to do 30 seconds
for a couple of repetitions of 30 take a
small break and do another one again
really what you're seeing here is
emphasizing the lower body we've moved
forward we've moved backwards we've
moved side to side we've moved one leg
at a time two leg at a time we've moved
the hip in all different positions and
we're building up a little bit of of
burn and a little bit of fatigue in the
system there is what we're trying to get
there we're kind of warmed up now we're
going to actually go into the
acceleration development part of the
warmup in this case we're going to do 10
m of a linear power skip kind of
skipping up and down so you're going to
do however many steps that takes you
kind of walk back and do two sets of
that we're working on acceleration we're
not going as fast as we possibly can but
we're starting to use this kind of
combination of move fast move a little
bit faster work on accelerating off the
ground but we're still building up into
maximum of 10 then we'll do a similar
thing in the vertical session so we did
this for a linear kind of power skips
for linear so out in front of you and
then power skips for vertical so how
high can we go
two sets of 10 m for that and now we're
going to go into linear bounds so we're
bounding in front of ourselves four
repetitions maybe three sets of that and
at this point we're probably feeling
pretty good and and we're popping so
we're moving and we're springing maybe
not necessarily 100 100% but with high
intent here and high purpose this is the
warm-up but this is also the the
training okay we're trying to get
something out of this we're trying to
improve our
acceleration okay after that those
linear bounds we get into something like
could get up so you're starting with a
down in a down position and you get up
to deceleration that kind of
exercise maybe three reps or three sets
of that or so for you know 15 M
something like that with an RP so a
perceived effort of kind of like 9 out
of 10 so we're again we're moving as
fast as we possibly can here we're
sprinting we're controlling that
deceleration but it's not like every
every every ounce of everything we have
until the last set and then we'll
probably do one at a true maximum eff e
CU we should be at that
level okay after that we'll actually go
into some Sprints 20 M Sprints maybe
three of them right RP so again you know
rate of perceived exertion on a scale of
1 to 10 of maybe eight for the first one
nine for the second one and then the
last one is a is a final 10 right you
can't do maximum effort on every single
thing but we're going to get pretty
close and we're going to get some stuff
done out of the previous one so that
would all be accounted for in our warmup
and acceleration hopefully that helps
you conceptualize how Travis is getting
this program started the warm-up is also
as you noticed preparation for the day
this is a very big component to getting
high quality training sessions in
everything should be intentional don't
just treat your warmup as hop on the
treadmill and run for 5 minutes do
something that's actually going to help
in your training later in that day and
even later in your program very highle
coaching from Travis here setting up
multiple benefits and getting you really
time efficient training there so let's
go ahead and move on and talk about the
actual workouts on the individual days
remember day one here we're back we're
focusing on acceleration and lower body
rate of force development with a touch
hypertrophy in order to get acceleration
done we already knocked that out with
our Dynamic warm-up right so we did that
we did our power skips we did our bounds
um we did some get UPS to Sprints and we
were really working on accelerating as
fast as we possibly can we haven't yet
touched on our lower body rate of force
development though we did some of that
in the warm-up nor our hypertrophy so we
would finish that initial warm-up
session finishing with that last
exercise being the Sprints and our next
block then is actual power development
so in this particular case there's two
exercises first one is a hang clean so
for you those of you that are unfamiliar
the barbell would start kind of mid
thigh just above your knees region and
you would catch the clean in in an upper
power position um you you can catch it
all the way at the bottom if you'd like
but a a a true hang clean is starting
not with put the bar ball on the floor
but starting with it elevated and then
potentially catching it as low as
possible so that's the clean exercise um
you're going to do something like three
repetitions for four sets and you're
going to do this at maybe 80% all right
uh RP is 7 out of 10 we're using this to
go fast but we're also using this to
develop technique so whether you have a
lot of skill or no skill at all we
really need to get good quality practice
in it is light enough but in fact if you
look at the research Peak power in the
power clean or the clean itself happens
somewhere between 70 to 90 plus% of your
one rep max so being at a 70 or 80% here
is going to produce a ton of power even
if you are moderately trained or
experienced with the clean exercise if
you're not familiar with the Olympic
lifts you can modify it potentially but
a phenomenal exercise in fact uh looking
at like sports science in general the
highest power outputs found of any
exercise will come with the power clean
the hang clean or the Hang snatch that
power snatch those exercises Trump
anything else you can do for total Peak
power production so a wonderful option
there again we're looking at four sets
of three repetitions non- fatiguing with
a lot of rest second exercise is going
to be seated box jump so you sit on a
box you explode from that seat jump up
and land on a small box a big tip I
would give you here though this is not
directly in Travis's program so I
apologize for putting words in your
mouth typically you want to set that box
that you're landing on to be much
smaller than you think this is not a
game of who can jump on the highest box
we're trying to develop power and we
need to do it in a way where we can
actually complete high quality and use a
lot of technique with our jumping and
really we're trying to make ourselves
better when we're in our Sport and so
putting a really high box up there where
we're in fear for our life or worst case
we're actually slipping smashing our
Shin against the box now we have to take
some time off of training or go through
a bunch of pain is not the goal here so
put that box lower than you think and
then just work on jumping higher than
you need to don't don't just jump enough
to get on the box jump as high as you
possibly can and get a lot of quality
out of that in his particular case he's
recommending like a 90 CM box which is
not particularly high and you're going
to do five repetitions per set four sets
uh if you wanted to probably super set
these things you could so you could
clean do the jump come back and clean do
the jump but you could do them
separately as well once we finished
those two exercises and we completed our
power development we're going to go on
to our strength hypertrophy and
rotational power couple of different
exercises here we're going to do a
barbell back squat as well as a medicine
ball perpendicular throw from a kneeling
position okay now with the barbell back
squat we're going to be doing 10
repetitions we're going to do four sets
of that and we're looking at a
combination of kind of you know 60% One
Max plus or minus so we don't want this
to feel like what we did in the Hy
hypertrophy workout I don't want you to
be completely exhausted taking this all
the way to the end we're just trying to
stimulate a little bit hypertrophy but
we're not trying to maximize it we're
not trying to get complete muscular
failure in fact in this particular case
he puts a restriction on barwell
velocity so no lower than 73 m/s the way
that this works is there are various
devices I Know Travis uses a particular
piece of call a gym aware where it
attaches to your barbell and every
single repetition it tells you the
velocity that you've achieved and so
what he's saying here is we want
hypertrophy but we don't want to lose
context of this is still speed
development and power development so if
you go too slow we're stopping you so
you have to still be able to go fast
enough in this particular case no less
than 73 met per second maybe a little
bit lower but not much more than that if
you're going way faster than that then
we probably don't have enough load on
the barbell so he's controlling the
situation the repetition range as well
as the load by controlling the speed so
it's a nice blend there of kind of going
after multiple things he's also saying
we're going to shut the rest Revel down
just a little bit we're going to go to a
minute and a half here so a little more
fatigue a little more buildup but but
not all the way to the end either now as
I said you're also going to combine this
with that rotational power so you're
going to use a 45 kogam ball from that
kneeling position you're going to rotate
and slam it as hard as you can four six
repetitions per set four sets total and
you'll rest a little bit more maybe 2
minutes between all those because we're
trying to develop power so a little bit
more rest the last part of the day is
now our knee health for Speed and we're
going to have three components of this
first is going to be a single leg squat
with a counterbalance really making sure
we can control our foot knee and hip
position as well as our upper body and
our torso alignment so not rotating left
or right or off center making sure our
hips and pelvis stay in alignment while
our feet and knee and and toe overall
are going in the right direction so
we're going to do that uh you're
probably looking at again six rep itions
per set you know per leg uh four total
sets and we want that to be at like 85%
difficulty this would be hard to program
as a percentage of your one rep max
because who knows what their one rep max
single leg squat is I don't can't
probably program this by your velocity
either because you're not trying to go
fast or slow RP would work here but he's
also just saying hey work pretty hard
but don't smoke yourself we want to
stimulate we don't want to annihilate
okay call that 85% yeah some people will
misjudge what that means a little bit
but we're getting pretty close here to
what we're trying to do and we'll do a
minute rest interval another exercise
we're going to do here is a Nordic curl
these are fantastic one of my favorite
exercises ever and one of the quickest
ways to get yourself into an internet
fight is to talk about your position on
the Nordic curls um it is a beautiful
exercise but it eight repetitions maybe
three sets here now your chances of
getting very sore hamstrings are high
and so he's keeping the load a lot lower
here by doing three sets instead of four
where the previous exercise is going to
be very quad dominant and your quads
typically handle that very well wants to
make sure you don't blow your hamstrings
out too much because we're going to do
more stuff tomorrow and so 85% here RP
again you know kind of eight out of 10
with that one minute rest then our last
last exercise is going to be ankle
strengthening exercises maybe three sets
of eight and really rounding oursel out
and keeping our knee in the healthiest
position possible now every week we're
going to progress this day one a little
bit and I want to just hit the
highlights of of how we would go about
that remember we're just in the first
phase and so our progression strategy
for our transmutation and realization
phase will be a little bit different but
really you have a lot of options this is
just the example and the way that Travis
went about it for this particular
program the warmup will stay almost the
same no real changes to that in terms of
exercises in terms of how many
repetitions how many sets or your effort
none of that really needs to change for
the entire four weeks here The Only
Exception are the last two exercises of
that Dynamic warm-up and speed phase
when we start getting into actually the
deceleration and the True full out
sprinting on the second week Travis adds
an entire new set to that but then
actually backs that set back off in the
third week and so he's dosing things
like full maximum effort sprinting very
very specifically and very cautiously so
add one more set next week and then
bring it back down and then add it back
after that and to really pay attention
to it but the rest of the warm-up is
pretty identical for the power
development section remember we're
talking about a hang clean as well as a
seated box jumps as we go from weeks 1 2
to 3 to four from Week 1 to two we're
basically just increasing RP so remember
week one he said you know can I say it a
seven out of 10 well week two let's go
ahead and take it to 8 out of 10 and
then week three we'll go back to that 7
out of 10 so really trying to keep
people healthy while progressing some we
also might increase the am of volume so
by the third week we would add an
additional set so instead of doing four
sets of three we're now added five sets
of three but because we've added that
set we've taken the RP back down to 7
out of 10 so he's playing with intensity
and volume a little bit and to be honest
with you while you might think these
subtle small changes what's the real
difference between an rpu 7 out of eight
on a power clean those subtle
differences are what make everything
work it is really how you keep people
healthy over years of training
I Know Travis has done this many times
taking kids from kids to adults to the
NFL and so making sure somebody stays
healthy over the course of 10 or 15
years is why these small things matter
to pay attention to as D well is
acknowledged they are important and
going from an extra set of three or
another
RP is what makes these things successful
so really subtle but important points
there that I didn't want you to gloss
over or just think a that's not a big a
deal I'll do four five six sets and kind
of figure out based on how I'm feeling
that day maybe but unless you're
thinking about that in the context of
weeks months and years you might be
putting yourself in a position where
eventually problems start to occur and
you don't know why from there we're
going back into our strength hypertophy
and rotational power emphasis reminder
there are two exercises there bar ball
back squat as well as our medicine ball
rotational throw as we go from Week 1 to
two we're going to allow a slight
increase in intensity so going from say
you know 58% of your one R Max to 60%
what this functionally means is your
speed's going to go down and so while we
kind of said hey a minimum of 73 m/s we
might say the minimum is now 7 small
change but will matter we'll keep this
going uh for the rotational Met Ball you
can't do much about that maybe if you
have a slightly heavier ball and you can
add a kilo to the ball that would be
great that would be recommended but
you're still going to keep the load the
same and you're still going to try as as
hard as you possibly can now as you go
into week three similar idea as we had
before um where we're going to go back
to the lighter ball that we used in week
one and we'll take our our overall
intensity like we used in week one and
we'll take that back down to allow us to
go a little bit faster and now in this
particular case we will hold the
velocity to like minimum of
087 and so we're progressing by saying
go faster at the same load at the same
intensity and that's how how we're going
to progress our final Block in this
phase is our knee Health three exercises
single leg squat Nordic curl and our
ankle mobilization stuff in terms of our
ankle strength we're not going to really
progress that you're just going to kind
of do the same thing as the weeks go by
but we really have an opportunity to
move with the the Nord curls and the
single leg squat so single leg squat
week one remember we're going to do
three sets of six at like
85% week two we might take that up to
90% difficulty so asking you to go
substantially harder in that but then
week three coming all the way back down
to like
75% so really making this is like hey we
put a lot of load and a lot of ask on
there let's really back off a little bit
um to not run ourselves into the wall
and then for the Nordic curl you're
going to see a similar thing 85% week
one 90% week two and then back down to
like 80% uh and even not only backing
down to 80% but we're going to back down
to sets of six instead of six of eight
uh to to give the hamstrings a break for
week four of all that stuff you would
basically come back and do a little bit
harder of everything and so now what
you're kind of seeing is we went hard
for week oneish but we tested the waters
and then we went a little bit harder for
week two and then week three we backed
down a little bit paid the price and now
we can come back week four and have our
hardest week yet and really go after it
this is a very smart approach and it's
effective it allows you to accumulate
volume while working towards higher and
higher intensities but to do your
hardest week week four or after one of
your easiest weeks in week three not the
other way around typically folks like to
just kind of add more and more and more
and they do their hardest week
immediately preceded by their previously
hardest week which was preceded by their
me previously hardest week before that
and that's fine for some outcomes like
hypertrophy but in this context this
kind of up down up down approach is
probably a little bit better if we can
now I would like to zoom back out and
get into our second phase of
transmutation
lots of details left and I'm sure plenty
of you were going oh my gosh I wish you
would stay there and go over more of the
days but as a final final reminder
you'll have to check out the PDF in the
show notes to do that because I do want
to get into our next one at the highest
level that's transmutation similar idea
four days each day has a big overall
concept and theme as well as four to
five subcomponents so day one for
transmutation is an acceleration and
lower high velocity strength and the
four subcomponents are always a dynamic
warmup
acceleration power strength for High
Velocity force and then finally knee
health for Speed so it feels very
similar you can see we're going to
progress slowly carry concept over from
the first phase into the second one
we'll change some things and then you'll
see some of these Concepts carry over
from this phase into our third and final
phase as well day two is an acceleration
and upper uh High Velocity strength five
components for this day so a little bit
long longer Dynamic warmup and change of
Direction now we've integrated single
link bounding if you know much about
petrics bounds are a harder and more
difficult thing than hops so in the
first phase we were hopping this is
two-leg like a bunny like hop hop pop
now we've progressed by going one leg at
a time and we're bounding so a bound
single leg landing on the same single
leg so by doing that we've represented a
little bit of progression of difficulty
we've also gotten more specific so you
see most athletes are going to be
competing in single leg situations so
when you're running you almost all well
you only ever have one leg on the ground
at a time when you're jumping you're
you're generally cutting moving um off
of one leg rather than both at the same
time so we've progressed from Dual leg
to single leg and thus by doing that
made ourselves automatically more Sports
specific now I don't even know the
actual sport uh this program was built
for I think maybe football but I'm not
even entirely sure but it doesn't matter
because by going from bilateral to
unilateral we've almost always made it
more Sports
specific so the third component then is
still postural supporting strength
fourth is strength for high velocity and
then again of course hypertrophies for
symmetry still investing in the body
still cleaning things up um but making
that a smaller component day three is
now speed and lower high velocity power
four components first one is our
athletic speed development and when
every time you hear this athletic part
so athletic strength athletic power
athletic speed development this
generally means we're doing things that
are more uh range of motion more looking
more sport are oriented to this
individual and their person so more like
what they're going to go through in
their sport so being more specific this
fashion second component for the day is
power third is power contrast which is a
different style of power and then fourth
is lower body accessory so these are
again particular movements that need to
be added to the program for hypertrophy
sake for strength sake um for injury
prevention for uh injury reduction known
injury history just lots of different
accessories we can add on there or just
things that we have thought we haven't
trained in a while that need to come
back into the program day four is in a
maximum speed and upper body strength
and power four components Dynamic
warm-up and maximum speed so now is our
first time we're actually really going
after true maximum speed concurrent
power athletic strength and then our
upper body accessory remember the day
before had lower body accessory now
today we have upper body accessory our
next chunk is power but if you remember
it's actually specifically referred to
as concurrent power and so Travis uses a
little technique that we call waving and
there's some other ways to think about
this in terms of contrast but he's going
to do five different sets and he's going
to wave the repetitions and the
intensity per set right so in this
particular case set one is three
repetitions at 80% of your one or Max
set two is two repetitions at
85% so one less rep but a little bit
heavier and then back to three reps at
80% and then two reps at 85% and so you
can see we went up and load down and
load up and down down and load this
helps you develop power over a higher
area of that force velocity curve it
allows you to also go heavier but not
get as fatigued because when you went
heavier you did one less rep and then we
finish it with a final set of one
repetition at 90% so it allows us to
really go high if you were to go back to
how I opened up and I talked about the
pipin chart your C Travis is also taking
advantage of that making sure he's not
doing to many too many total repetitions
across the week at more than 90% at more
than 80% there are General standards we
have there and so he's really counting
every single repetition to make sure we
stay within that total range now outside
of that the second exercise here is a
banded rotational chop five sets of five
at 65% difficulty again this is it with
a band or maybe a cable or row hard to
do velocity here hard to do kind of rpe
really outside of just saying hey give
me like 85% difficulty by 85 it's still
100% effort and intent that is critical
for power
development in fact uh I've talked about
this before but there is research
showing that intent alone even when you
actually move the same speed but
intending to move faster will result in
more gains in strength and speed than
when you actually still moov the same
speed but didn't try to move any faster
so really really important that you're
trying to move as hard as possible but
it should be about 65% because we're
trying to develop power so it should be
light and fast but not too light too
light is speed we need to have a little
bit of a load here and 65% is a good uh
number for this particular exercise so
that is our concurrent power now we're
into what Travis calls athletic strength
got a couple of exercises here the first
is a close grip bench press as well as a
med ball punch and drop step for the
close grip bench press we're doing four
sets uh of three repetitions and we're
going to be kind of in this 80 uh% one a
max range or so and he again he's going
to come back to our velocity so this is
going to be in the neighborhood of like4
m/ second and it kind of differs
honestly every set's a little bit
specific right here but we're trying to
work on different
components for our Med ball punch a 5
kilo ball or so for three sets of six
something like that and so again uh
transferring our strength kind of into
our athletic development and he's
combining that bench press with the
medicine ball throw to try to take the
strength combine it with the power
ideally thinking that'll transfer a
little bit better into actual sport our
last component for this particular day
is our upper body accessory in this
example we're going to use an overhead
press with a standing barbell we're
going to do three sets of three for the
most part um kind of in that same 80% or
so at a specific U velocity load
something like 04.5 meters per second as
a minimum he's going to combine this
with pull-ups same thing kind of three
sets for Speed with some load and then
finally uh TRX banded pulls uh for 12
repetitions so a little bit of stuff
going on there uh accessory work to try
to develop some specific adaptation in
this case in the upper body as well as
providing us overall balance to finish
this off now we'll go into our last big
phase
realization day one big focus is
acceleration and lower high velocity
strength five components here we're
going to go after acceleration and
realization then we're going to go into
acceleration and potentiation Peak third
is power fourth is strength for High
Velocity force and then five is knee
health for Speed day two is our speed
and upper High Velocity strength we got
four components today to deal with our
athletic speed number one our posture
and supporting strength number two
strength for Hy velocity number three
and then hypertrophy for symmetry number
four day three is a change of Direction
and lower high velocity power first
component is change of Direction second
is power third is power contrast and
then fourth is lower body
accessory day four is our final day
really and this is going to end with a
maximum speed and upper High Velocity
power our four particular components are
linear speed athletic power upper body
strength and upper body accessory I
should note before I get into the
examples here this last week of this
last phase would be a taper and so we
would get into backing off and peing
there so wanted to make sure we note
that as you look at the program and
you're seeing the the progression
throughout this last phase it's intended
to start the season or compete or
whatever we're going to be do at the end
of the last day in this last and final
phase sticking with our theme and going
through just day one and getting through
the warm-up we're looking at trying to
develop acceleration and
realization reminder realization just
really means taking the previous eight
plus weeks of training and realizing it
on the field on the court on the pitch
in the arena as actual movement in
whatever Sports you're in right so this
would be different the exercises would
absolutely be different depending on
your sport um so this is just the one
example we've got to go off walking
lunges for a warmup side lunge warm-ups
forward lunge elbow to inep to get us
going hip mobilization and a half
kneeling uh and elbow InStep to really
open up the adductors get them moving
hip internal rotation we've now added a
heel to glute uh and inverted hamstring
movement power skips pillar skips um 10
yard power skips plus a 10 yard Sprint
really starting to move linear bounds as
well as a half kneeling acceleration
Sprint to finish off that first initial
block for the day we then go into the
next phase which is acceleration
potentiation and
realization here we're looking at a
couple of exercises accelerated running
as our first thing that comes with
actually a load and release so you kind
of get loaded and released and you
develop acceleration there and then
actual formal sprinting so that load and
acceleration you're looking at you know
four sets of that obviously we're doing
something like uh
25% body weight and a restriction a lot
of people are familiar but some are not
with the idea of acceleration training
such that you can put a small load
imagine doing a Sprint and I held you
back to a load that is equivalent to 25%
of your body weight so you take off and
you run and you're accelerating and
trying to move as fast as you can but
you're actually moving slower because
you have a small load 25% in this
particular case we would do that for a
small amount a few meters and then we
would release it and you would then take
off and Sprint faster because you had a
couple of steps with that preload on it
that is a great way to develop
acceleration that is in contrast to a
way of producing say Peak
velocity in which you would do the
opposite so instead of dragging that
sled with 25% of your body weight and
having you go slower while you're still
trying to go as fast as possible if I
put that load in front of you and I used
it to pull you and I would probably only
use something more like 10 or 15% of
your body weight I would actually let
you run faster than you normally can run
without anything on you this is called
over speed training this is tremendous
for developing Peak speed okay now if I
go too fast with that I pull you too
hard I say use 25 or maybe 40% of your
body weight I actually ruin your
mechanics because you spend the whole
time trying to not just fall on your
face and you end up breaking and so you
want to give them a light tug there so
they can move faster than normal but not
so fast that you Ru mechanics you can do
the same thing with punching with
jumping with any other area this is
again called overspeed I published um
research on this before Dr Lee Brown
who's a colleague of mine at Cal State
Fullerton uh spent over a decade
publishing research in this area and it
is extremely effective not great for
acceleration because you're not
overcoming any load so that's why in
this particular phase Trav is really
trying to work on acceleration so he's
got a little bit of a load there and
will'll work on Peak speed or max speed
on different days wanted to share that
inside with you though right there a lot
of people just kind of think all speed
work and Power work is the same and they
just randomly and haphazardly throw
different drills out there and the
reality of it is it's probably okay but
that's certainly not optimal and it is
absolutely not the best way to go about
it there are different components and
there are different drills for specific
purposes and it's best for us if we use
them that way so getting us back on
track here the second exercise of the
day would be a true and traditional
Sprint uh this is something again short
Sprint we're trying to accelerate this
is 10 m this is starting this is getting
going because we're trying to just work
on that component
RP a 10 here a lot of rest 2 3 minutes
of rest or more and we're going couple
of sets as hard as we possibly can RP 10
and then a couple of them maybe half you
know two of them just at like a nine um
so really being careful with when we're
truly truly going Peak speed next
component then is our actual power
development a couple of exercises here
now we're looking at a hang clean where
we're starting specifically below the
knee as well as a banded hip flexion for
sprinting and something a component a
lot of people forget to work on is hip
flexion matters how fast you can do that
will determine how fast your knee can
get back into position reloaded and then
struck back into the ground behind you
to move you forward so spending a little
bit of time on that for the hang clean
below the knee we're going to use uh a
little bit of a staggered approach here
so two sets of two at 80% and then three
sets of one at 85% so really trying to
spend a lot of time in this power range
very low fatigue and a lot of power
output for the the hip flexion stuff
we're looking at you know five sets of
eight at about 50% difficulty you can't
and don't want to necessarily take your
you know hip flexion stuff to a maximum
fatigue there so just touching it
putting a little bit of resistance on it
helping it develop power is really all
you need to train the hip flexors our
second and last area is strength for
High Velocity Force production what
we're going to use here is a high bar
back squat as well as a depth jump a
30-in one plus a jump repeat so for our
back squat we're talking five sets of
three
kind of at a range of like 78 80% or so
of our one rep max and we're going back
to our gymaware and using our our
velocity something like 0.55 m/ second
as our minimum something in that
ballpark for our Jeff jump and our our
rebound um we're doing probably five
sets of four repetitions and we're
trying to you know jump as high as we
really possibly can and particularly
emphasizing that rebound highest quality
possible here our final category here is
our knee health for Speed couple of
exercises RDL from a deficit with bands
is our very first one so really getting
extensive amount of work uh in the
posterior knee range to keep that nice
and healthy four sets of five at you
know 85% want to be careful of again not
putting the back or the hamstrings and a
lot of fatigue but really also training
them with a minute and a half of rest
going to finish that also with some
single leg squats in a goblet position
so holding a kettle bell or dumbbell in
the front four sets of six here at also
85% with a minute rest now I know that
was a lot to handled if you're just
listening or even watching without
seeing the program in front of you but
hopefully there was a lot you could
glean and gain from that if you want to
follow the program exactly as it is
that's great if you're thinking that was
too advanced for me too complicated I
don't have access to all those things or
I want to be stronger but maybe don't
want to be an athlete feel free to make
modifications the uh with this program
the con Concepts will be true though
right we need to do all the things I
talked about at the beginning like
Progressive overload training multiple
planes work speed and power and
acceleration and all these different
components if you're trying to get those
well-rounded of adaptations so hopefully
uh you took something out of this no
matter what your situation and scenario
is I chose this intentionally for a
couple of reasons one I know it works
I've used this and very similar
approaches countless times with my
athletes I've used it personally and my
training for many many years in addition
Travis himself is an extremely
credential coach he has had a ton of
success he knows what he's doing and
then finally it is sometimes nice to
talk about what are the best in the
world doing what are these Advanced ones
you'll see if this is your first episode
or if this is your you know many
episodes into this series I like to do
both aspects I'd like to talk about what
can the everyday person do and then what
are the best in the world doing and I I
think that makes us all better
by seeing what both ends of those
spectrum look like so if I lost you a
little bit in this program I do
apologize but I think it was actually
for your benefit and maybe I didn't
maybe you're thirsting for more that's
exactly what you're looking for and you
wanted me to go deeper in either case
just let us know I would love to know
what all of you want to know more of uh
but I really do like this approach of of
going both ends of the spectrum want to
reiterate a couple of things before we
finish just because the program is more
complicated doesn't make it any more
effective per se on the same token you
may have a lot of experience or even a
moderate amount of experience and be
thinking to yourself that actually
wasn't that complicated once you get
into it more you'll realize it wasn't
actually it is pretty straightforward
when I look at it I was able to pick it
apart pretty quickly and so as you go on
or if you're listening to this and you
are Advanced I hope I didn't uh insult
your intelligence and to make this sound
more complicated than it really is
because it was really not that much it
is very smart it is thought through and
it is detailed which may then be more
complicated than used to but this is
what it looks like to be a highlevel
strength and conditioning coach for
performance-based
athletes I'm saying that to acknowledge
some many things here but one of it is
the fact that if you're going out to say
hire a strength coach there's a
difference right so high quality coaches
really think through every aspect I
tried to pull this out in my
conversation and discussion of this but
what I mean is how like a couple of
percentage points per week matter a
couple of seconds matter the order you
do things in the various components of
speed how we're progressing something as
simple as our first warm-up exercise
over 12 weeks a really highquality coach
is paying attention to every single one
of those details so if you are out there
looking and you're paying attention to
the coach you've hired or you're
interviewing another one for your kid or
yourself in your training they should
have this level of quality and if they
don't it doesn't mean it has to be this
complicated but if it hasn't been this
judiciously thought
through maybe consider another candidate
for that position because your best
service your best progress and your best
benefit will have this kind of care and
thought and diligence placed into your
programming if you're still here with us
at this point in the program I thank you
we covered a lot of ground today and I
really wanted to do an episode like this
because we've had so many people over
the years just say will you take me
through a program I know it's not
perfect for me I know it hasn't been
contextualized I know I know I know but
just give me something to to marinate on
and so I can see exact examples so
hopefully we accomplish that goal I know
it wasn't specific and applicable to
everybody and all your context but I
really want to do it for those reasons
let me give you some starting Place
anyone who's ever written everything or
created Music um built something from
scratch you all know day one is the
hardest so it's it's way easier if you
have a model to work off of even if you
throw that entire model away than it is
to just sit down on your computer and go
okay day one
squats okay it's really hard to write a
program like that create a story or
music design a house if you're literally
opening the computer up and you got a
blank Word document in front of you so
by using this as a model hopefully I've
made your life a little bit easier I've
inspired you maybe brought some
creativity in your programming maybe
gave you things to think about that you
hadn't considered before and also let
you know sometimes if you want to just
go very simple straightforward do the
same exercise couple times a week that's
fine too it clearly can work in either
case we walked you through as many of
the concepts as I could in training for
hypertrophy as well as training for
strength and power I picked examples one
that was a little more straightforward
one that was a little more complicated I
picked examples of programs that were
done in my view in my experience that
have been supported by the scientific
evidence in well-trained people most
people are aware but if you're not
there's a thing in the sports science
and training Community called the new
begin gains which is a a little bit of a
joke but it is actually scientifically
true such that people early in their
physical training tend to benefit from
everything and so almost regardless of
what training program I put you on
people will get stronger gain endurance
lose fat get more powerful and so that's
not really telling us is the program
great it's just simply telling you that
person has a low training age or low
experience so when I intentionally pick
this program I did ones that I know work
and people that are very well trained to
highlight the fact that this if it still
works in these people it's going to work
in all of you sometimes you can be
confused by programs that look like they
work because we took somebody again
who's untrained or has many been many
months or years since they've done any
training and so everything looks like it
works these work in a variety of people
these worked in men and women they've
worked in different athletes and sports
and so I really have a lot of uh a
confidence and support of these styles
of
training one more time to reiterate they
are not the only ways to go about it
block periodization as an
example is effective but there are
plenty of other styles of periodization
there's exercise choices there's
philosophies there's there's progression
approaches Travis himself uses different
ones in different context so lots of
options out there I hope this inspired
you to go learn more of them and for
those of you that maybe that's not your
passion you have a couple of examples to
work and develop your own training
programs out of or if you really want
you can simply take these ones as given
try them out on yourself and then see
what happens hopefully you enjoyed this
entire thing I had a lot of fun and
appreciate the time and attention thank
you for joining for today's episode our
goal is to share exciting scientific
Insight that helps you perform at your
absolute best if the show resonates with
you and you want to help ensure this
information remains free and accessible
to anyone in the world there are a few
ways that you can support first you can
subscribe to the show on YouTube Spotify
and apple and on Apple and Spotify you
can leave up to a five-star review given
that we're a new podcast subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot second please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they really are exceptional products
and services and then finally you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it if you have any
content questions or suggestions please
put those in the comment section on
YouTube I really do try to read these
and see what you have to say I use my
Instagram and Twitter also exclusively
for scientific communication so those
are great places to follow along for
more learning my handle is Dr Andy
Galpin on both platforms thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowerman if you have a
body you're an athlete